Quazi Irfan

Software Engineer | Data Engineer

quazirfan@gmail.com; Mobile 386 334 4792

Q github.com/quazi-irfan **in** linkedin.com/in/quazi-irfan **E** medium.com/@quazirfan

Summary: Bringing in uncommon combination of competitive programming skill, theoretical understanding of fundamental data analysis algorithms, and extensive research experience with the desire to join high performing team to solve complex business problems with simple solution with minimal supervision under tight deadline.

Work Experiences

• Data Engineer at Genus(ABS Global), Madison, WI

11/2022 - Current

- Developed, tested, and maintained data pipeline using Python, DBT, and SQL(Trino) to capture and transform billions of records and produced data products for researchers
- Collaborated with multidisciplinary teams to improve existing data pipelines and identify sources of bad data and apply fix to the pipeline
- Developed and maintained multiple dashboards (Metabase) to monitor ongoing data issues and KPI matrices to aid decision-making
- Improved data pipeline run time by $\bf 90\%$ by replacing Python script with optimized SQL query
- Provided **support for researchers** in writing SQL queries and addressed new data requirements by converting business requirements into data questions
- Continuously learning database technologies, such as B-Tree, Column storage and presenting it to team
- Software Engineer at Query.AI, Brookings, SD

01/2022 - 07/2022

- Built ELT pipeline in Python to extract data from REST endpoints and validated data using PyTest unit test
- Improved server response time by 80% by switching to Python green thread in task queue(Celery)
- Researcher & Teaching Assistant at South Dakota State University, Brookings, SD 09

09/2018 - 12/2021

- Researched drift compensation using **linear regression** to estimate displacement by double integrating acceleration signal obtained from inertial measurement sensor
- Researched **signal processing algorithm**(FIR and IIR) to smooth acceleration signal and different **numerical integration** techniques to integrate discrete time signal
- Built Java Swing application to draw obstacle map and visualized breadth-first search pathfinding algorithm \mathbf{Q}
- Co-developed R and SAS programming course and contributed to textbook 'Learn R through examples'
- Decreased grading time by 90% by developing automation scripts to grade x86 assembly programs
- Implemented string matching algorithm (Jaro-Winkler) algorithm to detect similar assignment submissions **Q**

Data Analysis & Programming Projects

- Applied Multiple Linear regression and feature selection methods to correctly identify useful predictors
- Improved **model prediction** accuracy and interpretability by addressing **multicollinearity** problem using Variation Inflation Factor, Ridge and LASSO
- Built classifier for **high dimensional fingerprint dataset** using dimension reduction technique (principal component analysis) and linear discriminate analysis
- Analyzed datasets using \mathbf{SQL} and developed JavaFX app that dynamically generates UI from DB metadata
- Developed data visualization dashboard (web application) using Flask, Pandas and Plotly and deployed on Linux VM running on Google Compute Engine behind Nginx reverse proxy
- Researched 25 years of Particle Swarm Optimization and implemented vanilla PSO in Julia and Python O
- Implemented backtracking algorithm to calculate Schur's number 🗘
- Implemented Markov chain Monte Carlo sampler in R and C++ to compute posterior distribution Q
- Developed assembler for SIC-XE instruction set in Java 🔾
- Developed Ada to 16bit Intel 8086 compiler using recursive descent parser generating three address code Q
- Built 2d side-scrolling game using Java 2d featuring axis-aligned-bounding-box collision detection **Q**
- Organized multiple ACM seminars on **Git** and **Vim**; Reported bugs on Unity3d and IntellijIDEA

EDUCATION & SKILLS

- MS Statistics (Fall '21) and BS Computer Science(Summer '18) from South Dakota State University
- Skills: Python(Numpy, Flask, Matplotlib, sklearn, statsmodels, Plotly, Pytest), R, Java, SQL, Redis, Bash, Linux, HTML/CSS, REST, Git, Github, Vim, Docker, Algorithm analysis, Relational database, Linear Algebra, Statistical Inference and Modeling(Regression and Multivariate Analysis), Bayesian Statistics

Publications & Awards

- Building exoskeleton glove on virtual reality platform Irfan, Q., Jensen, C., Ni, Z. & Hietpas, S., 2018 IEEE EIT
 - Bennett Fellowship recipient(\$5,000) to build game and motor-driven VR gloves to track finger movement and send haptic feedback when the real finger interacts with a virtual object(Research Blog on Medium)
- Inertia Measurement Unit-Based Displacement Estimation via Velocity Drift Compensation Using Ordinary Least Squares Method Irfan, Q., Ciarcia, M. and Hatfield, G., 2022 IEEE EIT

REFERENCES

• Dr. George Hamer, Ph.D.

Assistant Department Head

Associate Professor

Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Department

South Dakota State University

SECS 121

Brookings, S.D. 57007

605 - 688 - 5721

George.Hamer@sdstate.edu

(Instructor in CSC-314 Assembly Language, CSC-354 Systems Programming and CSC-446 Compiler Construction)

• Dr. Gary Hatfield, Ph.D.

Associate Professor

Mathematics & Statistics Department

South Dakota State University

Architecture, Math & Engineering Building 256

Math & Statistics-Box 2225

University Station

Brookings, SD 57007

605-688-5846

gary.hatfield@sdstate.edu

(Graduate research advisor and instructor in Stochastic process and Probabilistic robotics course)

• Dr. Marco Ciarcia, Ph.D.

Assistant Professor

Department of Mechanical Engineering

South Dakota State University

Crothers Engineering Hall - Office 210

Mechanical Engineering-Box 2219

University Station

Brookings, SD 57007

605-688-5908

Marco.Ciarcia@sdstate.edu

(Graduate research advisor)